Nancy Hale Papers, 1908-1989
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Nancy Hale papers
1908 - 1989
Hale, Nancy, 1908-
251
67 boxes, 8 volumes (33 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Author. Hale is perhaps best known for her short stories many of which were published in the New Yorker and in collected works. Hale's papers, provide significant information about her life and work; the relationships between writers and their agents and editors; the life of a modern professional woman writer; as well as topics such as creativity, human psychology, the New England character, and faculty politics in educational institutions. Material includes writings, diaries, photographs, speeches and correspondence with family and numerous 20th century writers.
Nancy Hale was born Anna Westcott Hale on May 6, 1908, in Boston, Massachusetts, the only child of painters Philip Leslie Hale and Lilian Clark Westcott. Descended from a distinguished New England family, Nancy Hale's grandfather was the orator, author, and Unitarian clergyman Edward Everett Hale, and two of her great-aunts were the writers Harriet Beecher Stowe and Lucretia Peabody Hale. Philip L. Hale achieved some success as a neo-impressionist painter of the Boston School, but probably had a greater influence as an instructor at the Boston Museum of Fine Arts School and as an art critic for Boston newspapers. Lilian W. Hale, the more talented artist of the pair, was well known for her portraits and landscapes in oil, pastel, and charcoal.
Nancy Hale began writing at an early age, producing a family newspaper, the Society Cat, at age eight, and publishing her first story, "The Key Glorious," in the Boston Herald, at age eleven. She also devoted considerable energy to the study of art under her parents' tutelage and, after she was graduated from the Winsor School in 1926, at the Boston Museum School (1926-28).
In 1928, she married aspiring writer Taylor Scott Hardin and moved with him to New York City where she was hired to work in the art department at Vogue. She was, however, almost immediately put to work as an assistant editor and writer instead. Under the pen name Anne Leslie, she wrote "chatty news" items, fashion news, and editorials.
Hale's true ambition was to write fiction. Jobs at Vogue and later Vantiy Fair provided financial support while she built her reputation as a fiction writer. While working full time she was also writing pieces on commission for a variety of magazines as well as free-lance fiction. Her first son, Mark Hardin, was born in 1930.
Hale's first novel, The Young Die Good (1932), was a chronicle of the shallow lives of the post-flapper "smart set" in New York. In 1933, one of her stories,"To the Invader," won the O. Henry Memorial Award Prize. A second novel, Never Any More, was published in 1934.
Hale was hired by the New York Times as its first woman straight news reporter in the spring of 1934, a job which she left after an exhausting six months. By then, she and her husband had been living apart for some time. They were divorced late in 1934.
In October of 1935, Hale entered into a troubled second marriage with author and journalist Charles Christian Wertenbaker. They settled in Charlottesville, VA, in 1936. Her next book, The Earliest Dreams (1936), was a selection made from the already substantial body of short stories published by Hale in such magazines as the New Yorker, Harper's, Redbook, and Ladies Home Journal. Writing was now her primary means of financial support.
Hale's second son, William Wertenbaker, was born in the spring of 1938. After several separations, she was divorced from Charles Wertenbaker in 1941. In 1942, Hale married Fredson Thayer Bowers an English professor on the faculty of the University of Virginia.
Her third and best known novel, The Prodigal Women, was published later that year. It is an immense book (over 700 pages) which, in the words of writer Anne Hobson Freeman, "dramatized, with unflinching candor, the psychological cost of being a woman at that time." It is the story of three women, each in her own way taking advantage of the freedoms offered by the post World War I rejection of Victorian social mores.
Throughout this period Hale was plagued by a series of physical ailments and bouts of anxiety severe enough to result in 1938 and again in 1943 in what was called a "nervous breakdown." Always intensely self-critical, Hale worried that she had squandered a promising career and sold- out artistically by writing to make money. She was fortunate in 1943 to find a psychoanalyst, Beatrice Hinkle, who helped her begin to solve what Hale called "this problem of who to be."
Always extremely hard-working, Hale published a collection of stories, the first of two much-loved volumes of "autobiographical fiction," A New England Girlhood (1958), and three novels in the 1950s. Hale singled out a favorite among these, Heaven and Hardpan Farm (1957). A humorous and humane novel about a group of "neurotic" women and their Jungian doctor at a small country sanitarium, Hale felt it was her most successful effort at writing about the experience of psychoanalysis.
In 1958, the University of Illinois awarded Hale a Benjamin Franklin Magazine citation for excellence in short story writing.
In 1961 Hale sold more stories (12) to the New Yorker than any other writer in the magazine's history. Also, in that year, she put together The Realities of Fiction, a volume of lectures on writing primarily given at the Bread Loaf Writers Conference, 1959-60. Another novel, a collection of stories, and an anthology of writings by New England authors followed in the 1960s. In 1968, Hale received the Henry H. Bellamann Foundation Award for her significant contribution to the arts. One of Hale's best-loved books, The Life in the Studio, was published in 1969. "My mother died and I felt more than I could stand without expressing it," Hale told a newspaper reporter in 1969. Advertised as "an affectionate recollection of some singular parents," The Life in the Studio is as much about coming to terms with their memory and their loss. Hale blurred the boundaries of fiction and fact to discover for herself "the meaning of the past," but also "to awaken an echo in other lives; to arouse a consciousness where perhaps formerly there was none."
It is clear that Hale shared her parents' artistic philosophy as described in The Life in the Studio. The artist's role is to create a subtle marriage of objectivity and subjectivity, to use "the interplay of the painter's subjective view with the way the light actually falls upon the object" to "render" its essence and its meaning. In Mary Cassatt (1975), a biography of the American artist commissioned by Doubleday and Co. after the success of The Life in the Studio, Hale was clearly aiming for "the special marriage of subject and object." Written with an authority quite different from that conferred by scholarly credentials, Hale combined personal knowledge of Mary Cassatt's social and artistic milieu with the style developed in her "autobiographical fiction" to produce a biography that seems, in many ways, ahead of its time.
Hale next turned her attention to stories for children, publishing The Night of the Hurricane in 1978 and, in the mid 1980s, writing a collection of stories for young dyslexic readers. She died in Charlottesville, Virginia on September 24, 1988.
It is difficult to neatly characterize such a large and varied output. Hale is probably best known for her short stories whose impact can be stunning. "...[W]hat I look for in a short story," wrote Hale in The Realities of Fiction, "is the reverberation of significance beyond the matters immediately under observation. I want to be able to look up from the end of the story and then, slowly, as what I have read sifts down, to have the flower of relevance open for me."
Her protagonists are most often women, usually rather well-to-do. As they go about their daily lives, skillfully drawn through careful attention to the minutest of details, these women come to an epiphany. Their moments of illumination bring better understanding of the patterns of their lives, but Hale's epiphanies confer what Hale's friend and sometime editor William Maxwell called "a sad wisdom." They are, in the words of Anne Hobson Freeman, "penetrating portraits of women who may seem calm, and even satisfied, but beneath the surface are struggling to retain their self-esteem and individuality."
In interviews throughout her life, Hale expressed amazement that the writing she felt was most private and personal evoked the strongest response in others. "I seem to do better by the world when I am acting for what is most inwardly myself."
Hale was described as elegant, regal, distinguished, and formidable, but with a disarming frankness and deep understanding. What writer Mary Gray Hughes called "a sense of risk along with the beautiful manners." Her writing reflects this complexity. Often described as "poetic," with what one writer called a "delicate balance of understatement and passion," Hale's "subtle and unsparing" work "depicts the quiet horror of life with a directness that is positively unnerving." Whether writing fiction, autobiography, or biography, Hale strove not so much for the literal, factual truth as for the emotional truth that lies beneath the surface. In a 1958 interview, Hale described most of her work as psychological. "I'm never writing about what I appear to be writing about. Anything that is worth conveying cannot be said directly."
See also "Nancy Hale: A Bibliography," by Norah Lind (2008)
The Nancy Hale Papers consist of 33 linear feet of biographical material; correspondence; diaries; photographs; subject files; and extensive notes, drafts, typescripts, publicity, and reviews of many of her speeches and writings. The materials date from 1908 to 1989, with the bulk dating from the 1950s through Hale's death in 1988. Though the papers contain some important earlier materials, Hale seems to have more consciously saved things after she became connected with the Sophia Smith Collection in the early 1960s. The papers provide significant information about Hale's life and work; her family relationships; the relationships between writers and their agents and editors; the life of a modern professional woman writer; as well as many of the topics that interested Hale, such as creativity, human psychology, the New England character, and faculty politics in educational institutions.
The main subject of the Papers is Hale's writing. The Writings series comprises more than half of the total bulk of the papers. Contained within it are manuscript and published versions of many of Hale's works along with research materials and notes which document the evolution of the pieces and the ideas motivating their creation. The notebooks in SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE often contain similar documentation of Hale's creative process, mixed with notes on a variety of topics. The drafts and notes are full of introspective explorations which are an unexpectedly revealing source of information about their author and about a variety of subjects of interest to her. Where available, the extensive drafts also show clearly the care Hale took in constructing her works.
The role of editors and agents in the writing process is well documented in SERIES VII. WRITINGS, particularly through the correspondence between Hale and her agent Elizabeth Nowell. In addition, the correspondence with writer and editor friends filed in the General correspondence in SERIES II, is also revealing. Of particular interest is the correspondence with William Maxwell as well as that with other New Yorker colleagues and a plethora of other writers.
Essentially a part of the larger Hale Family Papers in the Sophia Smith Collection, Nancy Hale's Papers augment the rich documentation of that distinguished New England family, primarily through the Family correspondence in SERIES II, but also through her writings, especially those about her parents (A New England Girlhood, and The Life in the Studio) and her great uncle Charles Hale (Charlieshope) in SERIES VII. Hale's complex and difficult personal life make her early adulthood correspondence with her mother particularly interesting.
This collection is organized into seven series:
I. Biographical Material
II. Correspondence
III. Diaries, Calendars, and Notebooks
IV. Photographs
V. Speeches
VI. Subject Files
VII. Writings
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected.
History of the Collection
The Nancy Hale Papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection from 1960 to 1997 primarily by Nancy Hale and Fredson Bowers with additional materials given by Eunice Blake Bohanon, Avis DeVoto, Harriet McKissock, and Craig Tenney of Harold Ober and Associates. Elizabeth Nowell's files were purchased from Nowell's daughter Clara Perkins Stites in 1990.
Search Terms
Beattie, Ann; Benet, William Rose, 1886-1950; Bevington, Helen Smith, 1906-; Bowen, Catherine Drinker, 1897-1973; Bowers, Fredson; Barach, Alvan L. (Alvan Leroy), 1895-; Chappell, Warren, 1904-; Chase, Mary Ellen, 1887-1973; Cassatt, Mary, 1844-1926; De Roussy de Sales, Raoul, 1896-1942; Ehrenpreis, Irvin, 1920-; Gibbs, Wolcott, 1902-1958; Grierson, Margaret; Hale, Lilian Westcott, 1880-1963; Hale, Charles, 1831-1882; Hale, Nancy, 1908-; Hale, Philip Leslie, 1865-1931; Hinkle, Beatrice M.; Hughes, Mary Gray; Maxwell, William, 1908-; Nims, John Frederick, 1913-; Nowell, Elizabeth; Panter-Downes, Mollie, 1906-; Rama Rau, Santha, 1923-; Renault, Mary; Sarton, May, 1912-; Steele, Paul Curry, 1928-; Stegner, Wallace Earle, 1909-; Travers, P. L. (Pamela Lyndon), 1899-1996; Updike, John; Warner, Sylvia Townsend, 1893-; Welty, Eudora, 1909-; Wertenbaker, Charles, 1901-1955; Wertenbaker, William; West, Jessamyn; White, Katharine Sergeant Angell; White, E.B. (Elwyn Brooks), 1899-; Hale family; New Yorker--History--Sources; Authors, American--20th century--Sources; Jungian psychology--History--Sources; Publishers and publishing--United States--History--Sources; Women journalists--United States--History--Sources; New England--Social life and customs--20th century--Sources
Additional Information
Related Material
Related material in the Hale Family Papers, Sophia Smith Collection. Additional Nancy Hale Papers are in Alderman Library, University of Virginia.
Appendix: Nancy Hale: A Bibliography
Download printable version: "Nancy Hale: A Bibliography," by Norah Lind (2008)
Introduction
Despite a writing career spanning more than a half century and marked by an extensive amount of published material, no complete listing exists of the works of Nancy Hale. Hale is recognized for capturing both the mentality of a certain level of woman and the aura of a period, glimpsed in three distinctly different areas of the country: Boston, New York, and the South. The three locations are autobiographical, drawing first on the New England of Hale's birth in 1908 where she remained for her first twenty years, followed by nearly a decade in New York City while she pursued her career, and eventually shifting during the late 1930s to Virginia where she remained for the rest of her life. Those three locales that she understood so well serve exclusively as backdrops for her fiction throughout her long career.
Childhood years are always critical to what we become, and Hale's background figures prominently in her life and her writing. She slipped, an only child, into a distinguished line of New England forebears, marked by the illustrious patriot Nathan Hale and including such prominent writers as grandfather Edward Everett Hale, author of "The Man Without a Country," and great aunts Harriet Beecher Stowe (Uncle Tom's Cabin) and Lucretia Peabody Hale (The Peterkin Papers). Her heritage connects her solidly to America's literary beginnings and repeatedly shapes her own writings, resulting eventually in a publisher's invitation to edit the significant literature of New England, which results in A New England Discovery. The second geographical site in which Hale sets her fiction, again affords a sensitive representation of an era and its players. Her glimpses of the fast-paced social life of New York City in the 1930s results in a steady stream of stories published in The New Yorker. Her more mature musings involve what is, for Nancy Hale, the somewhat puzzling world of Southern culture in which she finds herself by midlife. They are sprinkled with political and cultural satire of a more subtle nature than her earlier work. These three quite different views of America provide the backdrops on which Hale relies for her vibrant accounts. Hailed as a master of the descriptive glimpses of life apparent in her short fiction, Hale nonetheless proves on several occasions her masterful ability to handle the complexities of prolonged narrative.
Nancy Hale repeatedly addresses the challenging issues of her time despite periods of mental duress aggravated by the effort. In particular, she questions the female's role in society during the first half of the twentieth century, challenging the social construct of woman as merely wife and mother. Additionally, Hale takes on the biases of the world, particularly apparent in her fictional comparisons of the American South to the Nazi regime of World War II. She confronts the difficult subject of mental illness and the new approaches of psychological analysis in Heaven and Hardpan Farm. Her peers recognized Hale's fresh approach, particularly Scribners' iconic editor Maxwell Perkins, who claimed to intuit on meeting her that Hale could write. Her ideas are fleshed in with a descriptive subtlety which belies the disputatious nature of the content. It is the power of Hale's description which brings the fictional moments to life.
This effort lists and organizes the complete written works of Nancy Hale. Literary databases provide a limited number of entries. Hale's papers in the Sophia Smith Collection at Smith College and the University of Virginia's Special Collections contain extensive information about both published and unpublished writings. Nancy Hale's heirs often provided the author's own copies of her published books. Incomplete entries result from the difficulties encountered locating all stories in their original publications. Hale's own scrapbooks display published stories clipped by the author without an effort to include the publication's name or a date. Those listings are included nonetheless, providing all available information. To eliminate confusion, any missing material is indicated by an asterisk (*) as a reminder that the information is not absent by compiler's error. In addition, the symbol + indicates a literary work recorded by a reliable source, but which I have not personally examined. A single + represents a work which appeared on a list of Nancy Hale's writings which are held by the University of Virginia. A handwritten notation at the top of the list by Hale demonstrates her involvement in the recording process. The doubled symbol + + indicates writings of Nancy Hale, compiled by the librarians of the Sophia Smith Collection at Smith College, into a document dated March 28, 2000. Unless otherwise noted by bracketed authorial explanation, the appearance of a + after a list item demonstrates that the outside source provided all of the information in that entry.
The works are divided into primary published (A) and primary unpublished (B) works, as well as secondary sources (C) and awards (D). Major categories are further subdivided in a fashion appropriate for the material. Unless otherwise indicated, the items under each heading are ordered by date, beginning with the earliest. This list covers work produced by Hale between 1929 and 1980. The bibliography includes all material pertinent to a full understanding of the range of Hale's work; therefore, advertisements she wrote early in her career are included in addition to the more prolific fiction with which she distinguished herself. Hale's bibliography is a work in progress which will expand as more items from her large volume of published and unpublished work are discovered. In general, the early writings record the pulse of young womanhood, while the mature works demonstrate a depth fostered by the support of editors and friends from the highest ranks of the literary world. Her prominence in that world ensures her entitlement to this record of achievement.
Norah Lind September 2008
A. Primary Sources--Published
1. Books
This includes Hale's prolonged narratives as differentiated from the story collections which follow.
A1 The Young Die Good. New York: Scribners, 1932.
A2 Never Any More. New York: Scribners, 1934.
A3 The Prodigal Women. New York: Scribners, 1942.
A4 The Sign of Jonah. New York: Scribners, 1950. London: Heinemann, 1951.
A5 Dear Beast. Boston & Toronto: Little, Brown, 1959. London: Macmillan, 1960.
A6 Black Summer. Boston & Toronto: Little, Brown, 1963. London: Gollancz, 1964.
A7 Secrets. New York: Coward, McCann & Geoghehan, 1971.
2. Short Story Collections:
Many of the works contained in the following collections originally appeared in periodicals. The stories contained in each volume listed are indicated here, and those previously published stories are also listed in the section for periodical publications, identifying their first appearance.
A8 The Earliest Dreams. New York: Scribners, 1936. London: Dickson & Davies, 1937. Contents: "Midsummer," Mr. Britton," "For Art's Sake," and "The Great-Grandmother" were all published first in The New Yorker. "No One My Grief Can Tell," "The Waxen Man," and "The Earliest Dreams" appeared first in American Mercury. "To the Invader" appeared in Modern Youth, "The Double House" first appeared in Vanity Fair, "Mariana" in Harper's Magazine, "The Blue Muslin Sepulchre" and "Love Is Not Love" (+ +) in Scribner's Magazine, and "The Rider Was Lost" in McCall's. "The Artist, as an Old Man," and "A Fine and Private Place" were not previously published.
A9 Between the Dark and the Daylight. New York: Scribners, 1943. Contents: "The Six-Fifteen," "Though It Breaks My Heart to Go," "The Fair," "The Japanese Garden," "Cab-Taxi," "Gone Are the Days," "Between the Dark and the Daylight," "The Marching Feet," "A Place to Hide In," "The First One," "Halloween," and "Georgetown Nights" first appeared in The New Yorker. "Sunday-1913," "Book Review," "Who Lived and Died Believing," and "The Season of Summer" first appeared in Harper's Bazaar. "Those Are As Brothers" first appeared in Mademoiselle, "Odd Fellow's Hall" in Scribner's Magazine, and "That Woman" in Harper's Magazine. "'Days Become Dear'" was not previously published.
A10 The Empress's Ring. New York: Scribners, 1955. Contents: "The Empress's Ring," "Miss August," "The Bubble," "The Place and The Time," "The Readville Stars," "Object of Virtue," "Inside," "The Secret Garden," "The Copley Plaza," "Charlotte Russe" "The Snows of Childhood," "The First Day of School," "The New Order"--all published first in The New Yorker. "Some Day I'll Find You" first appeared in Good Housekeeping. "On the Beach" first appeared in The Virginia Quarterly Review. "The Fox" first appeared in Today's Woman, "The Growth," "Sheltered," "People in Places," "A Full Life," "The Year I Had the Colds," "But One Buttonhole Needful," "The Mocha Cakes," and "How Would You Like to Be Born" were all previously unpublished.
A11 Heaven and Hardpan Farm. New York: Scribners, 1957. Contents: "Miss August," "The Object," "The Model," "The Picture," "The Beam," "The Barn"--all published first in The New Yorker.